מזל טוב Mazel tov everybody. Today's דף daf is דף ט״ו. Daf
Tet Vav. We pick up at the bottom of ח׳ עמוד ב׳
Chet Amud Bet and the גמרא Gemara is now dealing explaining the
משנה Mishna that lists the holidays of the pagans, particularly these Roman
holidays, Saturnalia, Calanda, Calandia, I don't even know how to pronounce it,
anyway, but these are very interestingly a number of them right around
leading into the winter solstice and after the winter solstice. Right around
the same time that there are some holidays nowadays, both Jewish and
non-Jewish. Anyway, but
and again this is sort of interesting in the context of עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara because the גמרא Gemara is sort of window into
an awareness of, obviously you can't be oblivious of, you know, the
pagan world around you, and that's going to really continue today in
particular around something that really is very powerful in terms of like
how we like the date through which we date our שטרות, Shtarot,
our documents, and you know, and sort of how we frame our
time. You think about the way nowadays, right, we talk about what
year it is, what day it is and so on,
how pervasive the sort of larger culture in which we live is
that is very much, very much shapes your whole sort of time
frame. So anyway, that's what we'll get to, but now we're wrapping
up from yesterday the issue about this story here about what happened
in this period of leading up to the destruction of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash because and then and then the גמרא's Gemara discussion
about that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin moved from its position in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash in order to this place called the חנות, Khanut,
which sounds like it means the store, but רש״י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both say that it means just a different place on הר
הבית, Har HaBayit, but because they were not situated immediately in the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, they no longer could make certain types of
rulings and the initial point the גמרא Gemara says that they couldn't
do is they couldn't rule דיני קנסות, Dinei Knasot, fines, because fines
requires אלהים, Elohim, like this authority of סמיכה, Smicha, but this is
a very bizarre idea that not only does it require the authority
of סמיכה Smicha going back to משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, but it
actually requires the סנהדרין Sanhedrin being situated in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash itself. So the גמרא Gemara challenges this and says that that's
actually not true. We know they kept on judging, dealing with the
issue of fines well after the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So let's pick up with that on the first wide line
on ח׳ עמוד ב׳.
Chet Amud Bet. למאי הלכתא? Lema'i hilchata?
I have no idea. אמר רב יצחק בר אדימי למאי שלא דנו
דיני קנסות. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Adimi lema'i shelo danu dinei knasot.
Okay, or if you want to start one line before, let's start
two lines before. The lines get wide. ארבעים שנה עד שלא חרב
הבית גלתה סנהדרין וישבה לה בחנות. Arba'im shana ad lo charav habayit
galta Sanhedrin veyashva la bakhanut. Forty years before the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash was destroyed,
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin exiled itself and sat in the חנות. Khanut. למאי
הלכתא? Lema'i hilchata? For what law? אמר רב יצחק בר אדימי לומר
שלא דנו דיני קנסות, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Adimi lomar shelo danu
dinei knasot, that they were no longer able to deal with issues
of fines. דיני קנסות סלקא דעתך? Dinei knasot salka da'atach? Do you
literally mean that? והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב ברם זכור אותו האיש
לטוב ורבי יהודה בן בבא שמו. Veha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav bram
zachur oto ha'ish letov veRabbi Yehuda ben Bava shemo. However, let the
following, let this man be remembered for good, רבי יהודה בן בבא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava is his
name, שאלמלא הוא נשתכחו דיני קנסות מישראל, she'ilmalehu nishtachachu dinei knasot miYisrael,
were not for him, we would have forgotten all the laws of
קנסות. knasot. So the גמרא Gemara says נשתכחו, nishtachachu, what, we just
would have forgotten them? לגרסינהו! Ligresinu! Let's just learn them! Okay, so
it's not a question about whether we would know them as abstract
law. אלא בטלו דיני קנסות מישראל. Ella butlu dinei knasot miYisrael. No,
as a practical matter, we would have stopped judging קנסות. knasot. Why?
שגזרה מלכות הרשעה גזרה, Shegazar malchut harisha gezeira, that the wicked government
Rome made an edict שכל הסומך יהרג, shekol hasomech yehareg, whoever gives
סמיכה, smicha, passes on this aspect of, you know, rabbinic authority, will
be killed, וכל הנסמך יהרג, vechol hanis'mach yehareg, and anyone who receives
it will be killed, והעיר שסומכין בה תחרב, veha'ir shesomechin ba te'acharev,
and the city in which it takes place will be destroyed, ותחום
שסומכין בו יעקר, vethum shesomechin bo ye'aker, and the even the area
outside of the city will be uprooted, will be destroyed. So מה
עשה רבי יהודה בן בבא? ma asa Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava? What
did רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava do? הלך וישב
לו בין שני הרים גדולים, halach veyashav lo bein shnei harim gedolim,
he dwelt between, he went and he situated himself between two large
mountains, ובין שתי עיירות גדולות, uvein shtei ayarot gedolot, between two large
cities, בין שני תחומי שבת, bein shnei tchumei Shabbat, and he was
between, he wasn't in the תחום tchum of either city, presumably is
what it means. He was like outside of the two thousand אמות,
amot, the normal תחום tchum around a city. בין אושא לשפרעם, Bein
Usha liShfaram, between אושא Usha and
שפרעם. Shefaram. That's a place right
now in Israel. Okay, between אושא Usha and שפרעם. Shefaram. Now presumably
the point that they were big cities and big mountains were, on
the one hand, he wasn't in a city, so, you know, you
can't destroy a city, I wasn't in a city.
I wasn't in a תחום שבת, tchum Shabbat, he can't destroy the
תחום tchum of a city. But if you want to destroy it,
you'll have to wipe out a huge city, which obviously you wouldn't
want to do. If you want to level the ground, you'd have
to probably level an entire mountain. Okay, so that's where he was,
between אושא Usha and שפרעם. Shefaram. וסמך שם חמשה זקנים. Vesamach sham
chamisha zkenim. And he gave סמיכה smicha to five elders. רבי מאיר
ורבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון ורבי אלעזר בן שמוע. Rabbi Meir
veRabbi Yehuda veRabbi Yosi veRabbi Shimon veRabbi Elazar ben Shamua. So these
are of course the major תנאים, Tannaim, okay, the students of רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the generation before רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi.
So this is about the year 150, 170, something of that nature.
And we stop. So this is about the year 150, 170, something
of that nature. And we said that the קנסות knassos were nullified
forty years before the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, which
should be about the year thirty. This was about 150 years later,
okay? So a minute. So רב אבימי Rav Avimi mostly, רב אבימי
Rav Avimi added אף רבי נחמיה, Af Rabbi Nechemia, even רבי נחמיה
Rabbi Nechemia was one of the people who received סמיכה, semicha, נסמכים.
nismachim. כיון שהכירו בהם אויבים, Keivan shehikiru bahem oyvim, once the enemies
recognized what was going on, אמר להם בני, amar lahem banai, my
sons, רוצו, rutzu, run away. אמרו לו רבי ואתה מה תהא עליך,
Amru lo Rebbi v'ata ma tehei alecha, what can happen to you?
אמר להם הריני מוטל לפניהם כאבן שאין לה הופכים, Amar lahem hareni
mutal lifnehem k'even she'ein lah hofchim, I will be like I will
you know protect you, I will be like a rock that nobody
can move it, you know, and I will be here to separate.
It's actually interesting this week's פרשת בשלח, Parshas Beshalach, right? Where the
where the angel of God goes and you know between מחנה ישראל
machaneh Yisrael and מחנה מצרים, machaneh Mitzrayim, right? And it protects them
from all of the projectiles and so on. So here he is
standing between the two and
protecting them from all the projectiles. אמרו, Amru, they said, לא זזו
משם, lo zazu misham, and they did not move from there,
they did not move from there in the plural, the Romans did
not move from there, עד שנעצו לגופו ג' מאות לולניאות של ברזל,
ad shena'atzu legufo gimel me'ot lulaniyot shel barzel, until they pierced him
with 300, always an exaggeration, 300 spears of iron. עשו לגופו ככברה,
Asu legufo kichvarah, and they made his body like a sieve. Okay,
so you see that they dealt with דיני קנסות, dinei knassos, they
passed on סמיכה semicha which allows them to deal with דיני קנסות
dinei knassos minimally, you know, in the year about 150 years after,
well about the year whatever 150, 170, which was about 150 years
after you said it happened. You said that this stopped 40 years
before the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, around the year
30 of the common era. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק לא תימא דיני קנסות. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
lo teima dinei knassos. Okay, fine, it does not mean that the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin moved, they stopped doing דיני קנסות. dinei knassos. Okay, אלא
שלא דנו דיני נפשות. ela shelo danu dinei nefashot. It means they
did not deal with capital crimes. That's not just an issue of
סמיכה. semicha. It's true, you need סמיכה semicha to deal with anything
that's not a simple monetary issue. So even a monetary fine is
not a monetary issue, it's more of a power using the בית
דין Beis Din to punish, not just to rectify and compensate and
so on. So any sort of expression of the בית דין Beis
Din as a force and punishment, whether it's קנס knass or מלקות
malkus or מיתה misah requires this סמיכה semicha going back to משה.
Moshe. But so that's maybe explain why they use the phrase קנסות,
knassos, because it's בית דין Beis Din in its sort of imposing
of a punishment. But what we need to actually deal with capital
crimes is not just סמיכה, semicha, but we need the בית דין
Beis Din to be situated, the בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol,
the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. How do you
know that? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? כיון דחזו דנפישו להו רוצחין, Keivan
d'chazu denafishu lehu rotzchin, first of all why did they stop, why
did they move, why did they stop dealing with these cases? כיון
דחזו דנפישו להו רוצחין, Keivan d'chazu denafishu lehu rotzchin, since they saw
that there were so many murderers, ולא יכלו למידן, velo yachlu lemidan,
and they were not able to judge them, אמרו מוטב נגלי ממקום
למקום, amru mutav nigli mimakom lemakom, let us go in exile, כי
היכי דלא ליחייבו, ki heichi d'lo litchayvu, that these murderers and
couldn't judge them,
meaning that because of the you know there were too many of
them, they didn't have the power within society, maybe they couldn't catch
them, maybe there were just too many that they didn't have the
power within society, society was running amok, okay, and they were impotent.
So rather than be impotent and be in a position where you're
expected to judge and not be able to judge because of the
realities, better to put themselves in a position where they didn't even
have the legal power anymore to judge. Now some say that this
רוצחין rotzchin here refers specifically to the you know to the Zealots,
to the Zealots who were actually you know there was infighting amongst
the Jews, right, about how to deal with the Romans and so
on and you know there was actually people I mean you know
were using force and were killing one another besides killing the Romans.
So that this could also be because of all of that you
know with like the political murders that were going on, they also
just couldn't get involved. There was too much you know they didn't
want to be sucked into all of those political issues and so
on, they didn't have the power to deal with it. So they
said better we should be in exile. Now the interesting reason given
is the reason I gave is better you're in exile so you're
not accused not to judge it, you're not in a legal position
to judge, rather than your impotence is evident that you're legally required
to and you're not able to. But the reason that the גמרא
Gemara gives is כי היכי דלא ליחייבו, ki heichi d'lo litchayvu, in
order that they should not be held guilty, presumably means the murderers
shouldn't be guilty. But the murderers are guilty of you know of
a capital crime whether בית דין Beis Din is sitting there or
not. Now you could say well they shouldn't have a punishment passed
against them. But if they're not able to judge them they're not
having a punishment passed against them either. So I don't understand how
whether the בית דין Beis Din is sitting in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash or not determines whether you consider the murderers to be
deserving of the death penalty. In either case they're not being brought
to judgment and they're not having a judgment passed against them, right?
I mean רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, כי
היכי דלא ליחייבו רוצחין קטלא, ki heichi d'lo litchayvu rotzchin katla, so
the murderers should not be deserving of the death penalty, אין דנין
דיני קנסות ein danin dinei knassos etc. They weren't liable either. I
would have rather read it that the בית דין Beis Din wouldn't
be חייב. chayav. that it would no longer be the בית דין's
Beis Din responsibility, right, and that the בית דין, Beis Din, I
mean, you know, would not be seen as: hey, you're supposed to
be controlling society and you are failing. So better to put themselves
in a position where they no longer have that legal responsibility than
that they actually, you know, sort of like the גמרא Gemara I
think said before,
right, that the only reason, you know, it's that you're not צדיקים
Tzaddikim if you have the ability to protest and you're not protesting,
or what does that mean? So I would rather read it that
the בית דין Beis Din is not, doesn't, you know, that responsibility
for what others are doing does not adhere to the בית דין.
Beis Din. Anyway דכתיב, dechsiv, I'm going to finish the סוגיות sugyot
and then I will take comments. Okay, דכתיב, dechsiv, ועשית על פי
הדבר אשר יגידו לך מן המקום ההוא, ve'asisa al pi hadavar asher
yagidu lecha min hamakom hahu, you will do according to what they
tell you from that place, the place on הר הבית, Har Habayis,
מלמד שהמקום גורם, melamed shehamakom goreim, the place being right there in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is a necessary component of what it
means to, in order to judge דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. Okay, first
Michal.
I was just going to say about יהודה בן בבא, Yehuda ben
Bava, that he's considered one of the ten martyrs in the, during
the עשרה, asara, עשרה הרוגי
מלכות.
Asara
Harugei Malchus.
So I
don't know if they count exactly what happened then or,
right, because that
brings it a little
earlier, because like 130, 130, right.
So you might be right, you might be right because these are
the students and then, yeah, but these are all the תלמידים Talmidim
of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So you're right. So רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva בר כוכבא Bar Kochba is about 130, so right. So okay,
so this might be more in the 130-140 type of a period.
Yeah.
I would still venture to say that society would hold the בית
דין Beis Din responsible because they moved 15 feet away.
Right, right, right. Whoops, we don't have the legal power anymore, so
move 20 feet, move 15 feet back there. Yeah, I don't know
how to explain that, but okay.
Like a metaphor.
Yeah, if you
go to the wall and do this, any place except right where
the switch is, the light's not going to come on. So I
think there's some meaning to the specific spot. That's what they're trying
to say.
Yes, but the question is
we don't understand, I'm not, right.
Okay. No, his question wasn't the power of being there. The question
was how does it, right, how does it relieve בית דין Beis
Din of their responsibility, right, because they wouldn't do it.
It's sort of like a court
today is not likely to come out with a judgment that they
know everybody will ignore or disregard, because that's like an in-your-face rejection.
Whereas by moving away, people are still going to disregard, but it's
less obvious that they are, right.
All right, that's what I think, the less, right, it's less clear
that they are abnegating their responsibility or that their impotence is less
obvious because they're no longer in a legal position. But I understand
obviously how much does that really solve. Okay, let's move on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes and now we switch to the
focus of today's דף, daf, which as I said is fascinating given
the context of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah about how the whole discussion
about how we date our שטרות shtaros and sort of define the
dates that we're living in right now like just a minute ago
I was saying the year 130, 140, etc. It's all based on
the Christian era, right. So let's take a look here. מאה ושמונים
בסורו, me'ah ushmonim besuru, now this is going back to the idea
that says for 180 years,
what was 180? The מלכות יון malchus Yavan I think it was,
from the switch between the Romans and
the, right, it says before the destruction of the,
yeah, exactly, let's just read it again. Yeah, it says מאה ושמונים
שנה קודם שנחרב הבית פשטה מלכות הרשעה ישראל. me'ah ushmonim shanah kodem
shenechrav habayis pashatah malchus harasha'ah Yisrael. So the Romans took, you know,
took sort of took over the land of Israel 180 years before
the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so that's what
the גמרא Gemara said yesterday. מאה ושמונים בסורו, me'ah ushmonim besuru, just
180 years before the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. והתניא
רבי יוסי ברבי, vehatanya Rabbi Yosei birebbi, מלכות פרס בפני הבית שלושים
וארבע שנה. malchus Paras bifnei habayis shloshim ve'arba shanah.
So once there was a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built, so
now we're going to sort of do a rabbinic chronology here. Okay,
so here is the building of the,
here's the building here, I guess I'll draw my classic בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash here, okay, whatever, blah blah blah.
Where's the... מזבח? mizbeach? The inner...
okay,
whatever. Okay, here's your בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay, wonderful. All right.
I don't know why I'm doing this. Okay, so this is year
zero. Okay, not year zero, but year zero if we had a
different era. So the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the second בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash is built. Okay, so מלכות פרס בפני הבית שלושים וארבע
שנה, malchus Paras bifnei habayis shloshim ve'arba shanah, 34 years,
we have now this is פרס. Paras. Okay, remember because they rebuilt
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash under כורש. Koresh. מלכות יון בפני הבית
מאה ושמונים שנה. malchus Yavan bifnei habayis me'ah ushmonim shanah.
Now 180 years
you have יון. Yavan. So this gets you to 214. Okay.
It seems like you added, oh, is it not including the 34?
Correct.
Okay, so בפני הבית. bifnei habayis. Okay so one
hundred
and three here for the חשמונאים. Hachashmonaim.
Okay so that's three hundred and seventeen, one hundred and three for
הורדוס, Hurdus, right, which is under the and his family, right, which
is under the Romans, you know, all the major building that Hurdus
did etc. taking over from the Hachashmonaim, which gets you to four
hundred and twenty. So this is classic rabbinic chronology is that the
second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash lasted four hundred and twenty years. Now
we actually, you know, know from historians or whatever, that it lasted
I think five hundred and eighty seven years.
So that's a little bit of, a little off, only one hundred
and sixty years. Where exactly you make up that time. Anyway but
that's classic rabbinic chronology.
So they threw this up בפניה bifneha and after הבית. habayis. It
sounds like it's all the same starting from the same place but
it's not.
It means in the when there was the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
was present before the destruction.
Okay. Now מכאן ואילך צא וחשוב כמה שנים אחר חורבן הבית. mikan
ve'eilach tze ve'chashov kama shanim acher churban habayis. After that time when
you're figuring out how to date your שטרות, shtaros, if you're dating
it from the שטרות, shtaros, if you're dating it from the חורבן
הבית, churban habayis, so you should know that this is when the
חורבן הבית churban habayis occurred and starting there starts year zero if
you want to date your שטרות shtaros from חורבן הבית. churban habayis.
Zero years from חורבן הבית churban habayis starts there and any time
after that this is your starting point if you're dating your שטרות
shtaros from חורבן הבית. churban habayis. עלמא, alma, anyway, מאתיים ושית masai
ve'shis הווי. havei. So the Roman period was two hundred and six
years. It was after the Greek period. Isn't it interesting that they
consider the Roman period to begin immediately with the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, okay,
who were sort of rebelling against the Greeks, and even if you
know so a, first of all, you have Chashmonai rule and even
if Rome had larger rule of the region it didn't start exactly
here. But anyway but the גמרא Gemara says maximum you have two
hundred and six, which isn't one hundred and eighty. But again what's
the big problem?
Maybe the Romans sort of, you know, only started dominating the region
a certain amount of years into this period. Okay but somehow the
גמרא Gemara thinks that you have to go because the classic way
of thinking about, you know, the the period is Greek and then
Roman. We don't interrupt it with Chashmonai. So the גמרא Gemara says
this would mean that this is two hundred and six and you
said it's one hundred and eighty, the Romans before the destruction of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says ואת אמרת
מאה ושמונים, ve'at amart me'ah u'shmonim, and you said one hundred and
eighty? הוו אלא עשרין ושית שנין קמו בהימנותיהו בהדי ישראל. havu ela
esrin ve'shis shanin kamu be'heimanuteihu bahadi Yisrael. So here's the story because
we had this fabulous story yesterday that the Romans needed the Jewish
people in order to destroy the Greeks. I can't even begin to
get my head around that one. Anyway and they promised, they use
the תורה, Torah, which obviously the Greeks, the Greeks translated the תורה.
Torah. So anyway, the Romans kept their deal for twenty six years.
So the Roman period did not start until twenty six years into
here. Now again it would be so much easier to say that
the חשמונאים Chashmonaim just were, had actual real self-rule and, you know,
and autonomy, you know, for the first twenty six years, but it's
fitting it into its idea that the Romans made a deal with
the Jews and so on. Okay, so the Roman, anyway, the Roman
so here you have the twenty six years of their deal, okay,
or I would say just independent rule of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, and
then the Roman period began here. So this is the Roman period
and that was one hundred and eighty years until the destruction of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay. בהדי ישראל ולא אשתעבדו
בהו bahadi Yisrael ve'lo ishtabdu behu and they didn't take dominion over
ישראל, Yisrael, they didn't subjugate Israel. ואמטו להכי לא קחשיב להו כשפשטה
מלכות הרשעה בישראל. ve'amtu lehachi lo kachashiv lehu keshepasta malchus harasha be'Yisrael.
And therefore when it says when the government, the wicked government, took
dominion over Israel, it did not start from two hundred and six
two hundred and six years back because it only sort of took
dominion one hundred and eighty years before the destruction of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And that's where we're counting that period from. Fine.
אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa.
Now we get to dating שטרות, shtaros, which was implicit here because
it said if you want to start counting from the חורבן churban
you start from here. אמר רב פפא אי טעי תנא ולא ידע
פרטי כמה הוי לשייליה לספרא כמה כתיב.
Amar Rav Papa: i ta'ei tanna ve'lo yada paratei kama havei lish'aleh
lesafra
kama kesiv. Okay
so if the תנא, tanna, the תנא tanna who taught, meaning the
תנא tanna of this ברייתא braisa that we just talked that implicitly
says you start dating your שטרות shtaros from the חורבן הבית. churban
habayis. So there are two ways that they used to date the
שטרות shtaros and neither of what we do now. When you read
a כתובה, kesubah, what is the dating? The you know, you know,
what is it? חמשת אלפים ושבע מאות chamesh alafim u'sheva me'os whatever
ושבעים ושמונה ve'shivim ve'shmoneh whatever לבריאת עולם למנין שאנו מונים. livrias olam
leminyan she'anu monin. Right? Because the reason you say לבריאת עולם למנין
שאנו מונים livrias olam leminyan she'anu monin is to say which which
dating system you're using. Because that's one dating system, בריאת עולם. briat
olam. There's another dating system, לחורבן הבית. lechurban habayis. They used to
date שטרות לחורבן הבית. shtaros lechurban habayis. And there's a third dating
system which was even more widespread and more standard which was called
מנין השטרות. minyan hashtaros. And מנין שטרות minyan shtaros was from the
from basically was three hundred and eighty years. Before חורבן הבית,
Churban Habayit, okay? So מנין שטרות Minyan Shtarot is, so according to
this, is
26 whatever, well we'll get into this in a minute, but anyway,
380, 380 before חורבן הבית, Churban Habayit, okay? 380,
that was מנין השטרות. Minyan Hashtarot. It was sometime in the middle
here of מלכות יון. Malchut Yavan. Alright, we'll discuss in a minute
what that is based on, okay? And therefore that מנין השטרות Minyan
Hashtarot is the one that was the most widespread. So this year
zero would be 380, year 380 למנין שטרות, Leminyan Shtarot, and that
was the one that was used by the סופרים, Sofrim, by the
scribes,
and so now what we're going to say like this: If you're
this תנא Tanna and you are implicitly saying you start counting from
חורבן הבית, Churban Habayit, so if your counting is חורבן הבית Churban
Habayit but you get lost how many years from חורבן הבית, Churban
Habayit, go ask a סופר Sofer because the standard scribes, the standard
way the scribes date is מנין שטרות. Minyan Shtarot. Ask the סופר
Sofer what year it is and for his counting and you'll be
able to figure it out, like people know the trick of how
you convert the Jewish date to the, you know, to the secular
date, like you add a certain number. I'll tell you later. Anyway,
so if let's say, okay, we'll take in a minute why this
is 380, but let's say the סופר Sofer tells you, "Oh, it's
year, it's year 399 למנין השטרות." Leminyan Hashtarot. So what
year is it going to be here? 19. Okay. Now, the גמרא
Gemara assumes that you obviously know the hundreds. If you're off, it's
like, wait a minute, is this 5778, 5777, 79, like if you're
off, you're off in the, you know, in the single digits or
double digits, but not in the hundreds. So the one, so what
you need to know is you ask him, "Give me your last
two digits and I'll be able to figure out what the two
last two digits are for me." So what would you do if
you wanted to say how to get from 99 to 19?
You subtract 80. What's an easier way to do it because 80
is a big number? Just
add 20. I mean it sounds harder because you have to go
around the hundred bend. Okay, but if this is 401, okay,
right, this is going to be, right, this is going to be
21. Okay. So basically you add 20. Alright, so that if you
get lost here where you are, and the same will be true
way out here. If you don't have to worry about the hundreds,
just get the last two digits from there and add 20 and
you'll get where you are in מנין Minyan of the חורבן הבית.
Churban Habayit.
So why did they start before the Greeks?
We'll talk about that in a minute. Okay. So let's take a
look. איטעי האי תנא ולא ידע פרטי כמה הוי. Itei hai Tanna
velo yada pratei kama havei. If you don't know the פרטים, Pratim,
meaning the last two digits. הכלל Haklall means the hundreds. הפרט Haprat
is the last two digits. You don't know what it is.
לישאיל לסופר, Lisha'il lesofer, כמה כתיב? Kama ktiv?
What what do you write now in your שטרות? Shtarot? וניטפי עלייהו
עשרין שנין. Venitfei aleiyhu esrin shanin.
Add 20 years. ומשתכח ליה חומריה. Umishtakach lei chumrei. And you'll find
then your
result. Okay. וסימנך Vesimanach
and the way you can remember that you have to add 20
years is זה לי עשרים שנה בביתך. Ze li esrim shana beveitecha.
This is me 20 years in your house, okay? So maybe there's
a little play here about בית, Bayit, you know, and the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash and the Jews in the house of the non-Jews,
you know, so going based on your counting and so on, okay?
Because this of course is a secular counting, right? This is widespread
in the ancient world, which the Jews adopted. And I'll discuss the
significance of this date in a minute. This is the Jewish counting.
So זה לי, Ze li, here I am in the Jewish עשרים
שנה בביתך, esrim shana beveitecha, you know, I'm going here adding 20
years if I was counting like from your counting to add 20
years. Okay.
Now it says similarly, איטעי סופר. Itei sofer.
If the scribe gets lost, "Wait a minute, what's the double digit
I'm up to here?" So go ask the guy who's counting from
the חורבן הבית Churban Habayit and subtract 20. Alright, it's the same
thing in reverse. Okay.
Now, where were we? איטעי סופר נישייליה לתנא כמה חשיב. Itei sofer
nishayilei leTanna kama chashiv. Let him ask the תנא. Tanna. וניבצר מינייהו
עשרין שנין. Venivtzar mineiyhu esrin shanin.
And subtract 20 and ומשתכח ליה חומריה umishtakach lei chumrei and you'll
find your result. Okay. וסימנך. Vesimanach. And the way to remember it
is ספרא בציריא. Safra betziria.
A סופר Sofer reduces because like the idea of the way רש"י
Rashi says is that if a סופר Sofer is writing a ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, he has to be very careful with the extra
letters and the missing letters. Okay. If you take a look at
the side, the side gives another explanation why it means a סופר
Sofer reduces, you know, or remove, פירוש מנהג הכותב נקרא לכתוב בחסר,
Peirush minhag hakotev nikra lichtov bechaser, כגון משה בלא ואו, kegon Moshe
belo Vav, לאמר בלא ואו. lemor belo Vav.
Okay. So anyway, so you write your words are written in not
in the full spelling. It's just sort of a version of רש"י.
Rashi. תנא תוספאה. Tanna Tosefa'ah.
But a תנא Tanna adds. And רש"י Rashi says like a תנא
Tanna teaches a תוספתא. Tosefta. So the word תוספתא Tosefta and תנא.
Tanna. So if you start with the idea of 20, if you're
going by the Tanna-itic counting, by the Jewish counting. So the word
תוספתא Tosefta and תנא. Tanna. So if you start with the idea
of 20, if you're going by the Tannaitic counting, by the Jewish
counting, it's so תנא Tanna adds, תנא תוספתא. Tanna Tosefta. You add
20 to the secular dating and you'll get your year. If you're
going, if you're trying to convert in the opposite direction, so you
deduce- you deduct the 20. All right, so very straightforward. Now, why
is this 380- now why is it, what is it counting from?
This 380 year. So if you do it based on this Rabbinic
counting, right, 206 plus 180, right, is 386. So
it's basically the very beginning of מלכות יוון Malchus Yavan minus six
years. All right.
So what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, that's a lot,
that's not drawn to proportion. What the גמרא Gemara is going to
say is these first six years of מלכות יוון, Malchus Yavan, it
was not yet a global power, it was more of a local
power, okay, and it only became a global power here and what
we're really counting is 380 years from the period of Alexander of
Macedonia, right, Alexander the Great, we're counting 380 years from when he,
you know, when Greece had a like world dominion. Okay, and it's
counting from the beginning of the Greek period. Now why should Jews
count from the beginning of the Greek period? No good reason, except
that that was the standard counting. Okay, when Alexander took over, whatever,
you know at this period, obviously he set a new calendar and
that became the way in which the ancient world would count was
from this. Yes? It's like saying 2018.
It's like saying 2018, right?
It's not, you know, that's just the way people count. That was
מניין שטרות. Minyan Shtarot. Now the reality though is, is that because
remember I told you that they cut out here about 180 years
from the 160 whatever it was, 60 years from the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, the reality is is that this is not when Alexander
sort of took dominion. This actually, מניין שטרות Minyan Shtarot actually is
based on the beginning of the Seleucid Empire, okay, which is after,
right, the generation sort of after, well it doesn't make up the
whole 160 missing years. But anyway, it is based on the beginning
of the Seleucid Empire. The Seleucid Empire actually rose to prominence in
about the year 312 before the Common Era. So the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash was destroyed in the year 70, the Seleucid Empire was
312 before the Common Era, so this מניין שטרות Minyan Shtarot is
from the beginning of the Seleucid Empire. Okay, and that was the
standard way of counting in- of dating documents in the ancient world.
Yes.
So that would be really all of
these
powers that held sway over Israel. The Seleucid Empire, when Alexander, he
was favorable to the Jews. Right.
Right.
Exactly, exactly. Okay. So it is a little bit of funny, right?
Like we're talking about, we're counting based on, you know, this גויישה
Goyishe counting, right? It's even funny, why are we counting from a
terrible, a tragedy of the destruction of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
But anyway, at least that maybe makes us look back and sort
of hope for the rebuilding of it, right? At least it's a
Jewish counting, whether it's a good- a good starting point or a
bad starting point. You know, counting from this is just because hey,
you know, we're living under the non-Jews and this is their counting
and we're just- you know, and we- that's just the way things
work out. I mean, that's just sort of shapes our per- you
know, our way of thinking. How do you do from- I have
to see if I can remember how you do from the Jewish
date to the secular date. We are now, what are we now?
5788, right? 78, I mean. See, I also get lost. Okay. Anyway.
And we are and we are 2018.
So basically if you basically add 40, you know, I mean 40,
you know, I mean if you want to just focus on this,
right, you add 40 to get there. Okay, and if you want
to actually do the whole conversion, whatever, anyway, you add, I don't
know what it is. Anyway. Okay. So luckily these final digits actually
work out. So if you ever get lost with one or the
other, but that only works after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. If you
add 78 plus 40 is 118. I mean, if you're just looking
at the last two digits. If you ever get confused about the
last two digits, okay, you either like- you add 60 to get
up there or whatever. I mean, it's- you can either call it
60 or 40 depending on what you want to add or subtract.
All right. But it only works after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and
before- whatever.
It only works for like nine months. What?
Doesn't it eventually get out of whack?
No, but for nine months it works. When you get to a
new year on either side, you get off for three months.
Between January and ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. Right. Between January and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is when
it works. All right. Anyway. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. תנא דבי אליהו. Tanna D'vei Eliyahu. We learned from the house
of Eliyahu. ששת אלפי שנה הוי עלמא. Sheshet alfei shana havei alma.
So this was this- you know, way in which- six- this is
very widespread, sort of understanding that the world is going to last
for 6,000 years, like it works on a שבת Shabbos type of
a cycle. The 7,000th year is like שבת, Shabbos, is עולם הבא.
Olam HaBa. You know. And also, by the way, there was a
lot which the ראשונים Rishonim did, the רמב"ן Ramban in particular his
commentary on- on the first פרק perek of בראשית, Bereishit, of matching
up each 1,000 year period to one of the days of בראשית,
Bereishit, because אלף שנים בעיניך, Elef shanim b'einecha, you know, what is
it- because- one day for God is a thousand years, so sort
of matching it up to the symbolism of what happened in each
day of creation. Anyway, so here we say שית אלפי שני הוי
עלמא, Sheis alfei shnei havei alma, the world is 6,000 years. שני
אלפים תהו, Shnei alafim tohu, the very use of the word תהו
tohu here already evokes that idea of תהו ובהו, tohu vavohu, right?
The first 2,000 years were like void and waste. There was like
no תורה. Torah. אברהם Avraham had not yet really come onto the
scene. So, you know, that was all waste. שני אלפים תורה, Shnei
alafim Torah, for 2,000 years you had תורה. Torah. ושני אלפים ימות
המשיח, ushnei alafim yemot Hamashiach, the last 2,000 years is a period
which is presumably fitting for משיח Mashiach to come.
ובעונותינו שרבו, Uva-avonoteinu sherabu, but in our great iniquities, יצאו מהן מה
שיצאו, yatzo mehen ma she-yatzo, we've already got well into the second,
to the last 2,000 years and משיח Mashiach still hasn't come. Okay,
יצאו מהן מה שיצאו מהן. yatzo mehen ma she-yatzo mehen. שני אלפים
תורה מאימת? Shnei alafim Torah me-eimat? Now when does the 2,000 years
of תורה Torah start? אילימא ממתן תורה, Ee-leima mimatan Torah, presumably you're
saying from מתן תורה. Matan Torah. But problem is מתן תורה Matan
Torah happened after the year 2,000 from the creation of the world.
Now רש"י Rashi goes through the whole dating. I'm going to ask
you to trust me on this here. Okay? I do not want
to go through all the פסוקים psukim in בראשית, Bereishit, but basically,
here, we'll just erase some of this. Okay, 1948. Exactly, that's how
I remember it too. Okay, that is exactly how I remember it.
אברהם Avraham is born the same year the state of Israel is
born לפי מנין הגויים. lefi minyan hagoyim. Okay, so אברהם, Avraham, you
know why this is אברהם, Avraham, anyway, אברהם Avraham is born in
from בריאת העולם. briat ha-olam. Okay, so if basically and we say
that if you think that אברהם Avraham now, אברהם Avraham has יצחק,
Yitzchak, okay,
here's יצחק, Yitzchak, next generation. How old is אברהם Avraham when he
has יצחק? Yitzchak? Pop quiz, 100 years old. 2048. And the way
the rabbis make the idea that your זרע zera will be, you
know, strangers in a strange land for 400 years work because the
dates don't work, is to say the 400 years starts counting from
the birth of יצחק. Yitzchak. Because יצחק Yitzchak was already אברהם's Avraham's
child in a strange land. They didn't yet have control and dominion
over the land of כנען. Knaan. So the 400 years starts there.
Okay, so you have 400 years until the Exodus.
Okay, and יעקב Yaakov goes down, the classic idea, רדו שמה, redu
shama, the 210 years is when יעקב Yaakov and his whole family
goes down. Okay, I don't know why this is all of his
family. That is all of his כל זרעו. kol zaro. Okay, anyway,
that's יעקב, Yaakov, you know, going down. So from the time he
goes down till they're there, that's 210 years. Anyway, so that's the
basic story and then you've got the Exodus. So and then you
have הר סיני Har Sinai of course, coming soon after. I hope
everybody gives me extra credit for my wonderful picture. Okay, anyway, that's
I don't know, that's fire or something. Anyway, okay, so, okay, so
here's the story. That year is 2448. So where are your, what
do you mean the second 2,000 is תורה? Torah? תורה Torah only
starts in the year not 2,000 but the year 2,448. Okay? So
it says,
okay, מאימת ממתן תורה? Me-eimat mimatan Torah? If you're counting from
מתן תורה, Matan Torah, עד השתא ליכא כולי האי? ad hashta leka
kulei hai? But from there till now is like it's not as
much, meaning if you start this counting as this as the year
2,000, you'll be off. Because there's fewer, you know, from whatever date
we're
in, it's you know, this is not the year 2,000. That's you
know,
so דכי מעיינת בה תרי אלפי ופרטי דהאי אלפא הוא דהוו. dechi
me-aynat bah trei alfei upratei de-hai alfa hu de-havei. If you actually
look in, it's not 2,000 years, it's 2,000 years plus something else.
Though something else was a big something else, 448 years. It's not
just 2,000 years. So what do you mean? אלא מן הנפש אשר
עשו בחרן. Ela min hanefesh asher asu ve-Charan. The verse "the souls
they made in חרן," Charan, which we say means that he converted
people to the תורה Torah or to God, to belief in God.
וגמירי, Vegmiri, we have a tradition דאברהם בהיא שעתא בר חמשין ותרתי
הוה. de-Avraham be-hee sha'ata bar chamshin ve-tartei havei. He was 52 years
old. So if אברהם Avraham was 52 years old here, right? If
he was born 1948, the year 2,000 אברהם Avraham is 52. Okay?
And if that's the year he's still in חרן, Charan, but there
he is preaching the, you know, God and converting people and making
people believe in God, so it's a variation of what Michal said
that אברהם Avraham kept the תורה. Torah. Okay, אברהם Avraham doesn't go
down to כנען, Knaan, God only speaks to אברהם Avraham when? 75.
Okay? So actually this is even before God tells אברהם Avraham לך
לך. Lech Lecha. Alright, לך לך Lech Lecha appears somewhere here. Okay?
But anyway, but we're going to say that אברהם Avraham already started
bringing people close to God. So we're going to count the years
of תורה Torah from there. So, אברהם בהיא שעתא בר חמשין ותרתי
הוה. Avraham be-hee sha'ata bar
chamshin ve-tartei havei.
So actually, this is even before God tells אברהם Avraham לך לך.
Lech Lecha. All right, לך לך Lech Lecha appears somewhere here. Okay.
But anyway, but we're going to say that אברהם Avraham already started
bringing people close to God, so we're going to count the years
of תורה Torah from there.
So of אברהם בהיא שעתא בר חמשין ותרתין הוה, Avraham ba-hee sha-ata
bar ham-shin ve-tar-tin ha-va, he was sixty-two. כמה בציר מדקתני תנא ארבע
מאה וארבעין ותמניא שנין הויין. Ka-ma bat-zeer mi-de-ta-nee ta-na ar-ba may-ah ve-ar-ba-een
ve-tam-ne-ya sha-neen ha-vyen. So how many years are we short, meaning if
we were to start it here, we would have cut into this
period by four hundred and forty-eight years. Okay, and that's the so
counting of the תנא tana because here we're sort of counting based
on, you know, the בריאת עולם briat olam and the years of
תורה Torah and so on. So therefore,
where were we? הויין. ha-vyen. Okay, so so that sort of explains
it if we count the years of תורה Torah starting here. Now
if you think about it, if you start years of תורה Torah
starting here, right, so then how much from here till like the
חורבן הבית churban ha-bayit etc.? So so the פסוקים pesukim say that
they built the בית המקדש, beit ha-mikdash, right, רש״י Rashi quotes this.
Where where did they build the בית המקדש? beit ha-mikdash? Four hundred
and eighty years from יציאת מצרים. yetziat mitzrayim. Okay, so four hundred
and eighty years from this is going to be two thousand eight
hundred nine hundred twenty-eight. Two thousand nine hundred and twenty-eight is בית
beit is is בית ראשון. bayit rishon. I don't know why that's
a בית המקדש, beit ha-mikdash, whatever. Okay, בית ראשון bayit rishon looks
like תפילין. tefillin. Okay, בית ראשון, bayit rishon, some
say that like whatever there was a three thousand year celebration.
Now four hundred ten of the בית ראשון, bayit rishon, חורבן הבית,
churban ha-bayit,
okay, seventy years, four hundred twenty, okay this is the חורבן churban
of the second בית המקדש, beit ha-mikdash, okay, so that's what, eight
hundred twenty, eight hundred thirty, nine hundred. Nine hundred, so that's three
eight two eight
is the חורבן churban of the second בית המקדש. beit ha-mikdash. You
add another one hundred and
seventy-two, okay, the year one so one hundred seventy-two, this is the
end of the year four thousand. What year is that according to
מנין הגויים? minyan ha-goyim? So one hundred seventy-two after the destruction of
the בית המקדש beit ha-mikdash is basically like two hundred forty-two of
the common era, which is right around the end of the period
of the תנאים tana-im and the beginning of the period of the
אמוראים. amora-im. So it's interesting that they say that that's when the
end of the תורה Torah period, because obviously they would, you know,
at least the period of the גמרא gemara extends another few hundred
years. All right, so now the גמרא gemara says like this, okay,
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, אי
טעי תנא ולא ידע פרטי כמה הוה, I ta-ee ta-na ve-lo yada
pratei kama hava, לישייליה לספרא. le-shai-lay lay-safra. Now if you want to
be counting
from basically בריאת עולם, briat olam, you know, or you want to
be counting from,
or רש״י Rashi says, wait a minute, right, if you want to
be counting from like the the year four thousand, if you want
to be counting from this period, all right, so let's say,
you know, which is a variation of counting of בריאת עולם, briat
olam, right?
If you're counting from the year four thousand and you're going to
say this is the year, I don't know, four thousand one hundred,
right, it's a variation of counting from בריאת עולם briat olam because
really from, I mean, meaning if you're going to turn this into
zero counting from the year four thousand, the end of this תורה
Torah period, so you're going to call this the year one hundred.
So you're really four thousand one hundred from from בריאת עולם, briat
olam, right? You just start dropping off the four thousand. So we've
dealt with מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot, we've dealt with the מנין minyan
of the חורבן הבית, churban ha-bayit, this is a third מנין minyan
which is being framed as from the year four thousand, but it's
a variation of the idea of the מנין לבריאת עולם. minyan li-briat
olam. So now let's say you're counting with בריאת עולם briat olam
or from the year four thousand and you forgot which number you're
up to. Okay, so how are you going to know? So you're
going to figure it out based on the מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot,
all right? So where is this מנין שטרות? minyan shtarot? So if
this מנין, minyan, if this חורבן הבית, churban ha-bayit,
right, when did we say the מנין שטרות minyan shtarot was? It
was year three hundred eighty for חורבן הבית, churban ha-bayit, right? Remember
that? So this for the מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot, if you add
three hundred eighty, will be five hundred fifty-two. Okay, that's what that's
going to be, the מנין שטרות. minyan shtarot. So if you don't
know where you are here, you're going to be working with the,
you would either take this number and and and subtract fifty-two or
add forty-eight and you'll be able to get your last two digits.
Okay, so let's take a look.
אי טעי תנא ולא ידע פרטי כמה הוה, I ta-ee ta-na ve-lo
yada pratei kama hava, לישייליה לספרא, le-shai-lay lay-safra, go ask the סופר
sofer who's counting למנין שטרות. le-minyan shtarot. כמה כתיב ביה, Kama ketiv
bei, וניטפי עלייהו ארבע ותמני. ve-nit-pay a-lai-hu ar-ba ve-tam-ne. Take this number
and add forty-eight and then you'll get the last two digits. Okay?
So if the year zero is the year three hundred eighty and
this the year four thousand is the year five hundred fifty-two, so
if you're counting לבריאת עולם, li-briat olam, you're counting from the year
four thousand, just add forty-eight there and you'll get your last two
digits.
וניטפי עלייהו ארבע ותמני, ve-nit-pay a-lai-hu ar-ba ve-tam-ne, ומשכח ליה לחושבניה, u-mish-kach
lay le-chush-ba-nay, you'll find your, you know, your result. וסימנך ve-see-ma-nach and
the way to know this is ארבעים
ושמונה עיר, arba-im ve-shmonah ir, forty-eight cities. Okay, there's a number forty-eight
in the תורה. Torah. I don't know how that's tied into the
significance, but we have the number forty-eight.
The ערי לוי? are-ee Levi?
Yeah, exactly. The the לוי Levi cities. ואי טעי ספרא, Ve-i ta-ee
safra, now if you're the guy doing מנין שטרות minyan shtarot and
you forgot your last two digits. Go find out what the number
is לבריאת עולם li-Vriyat Olam and you know either add 52 or
subtract 48. Okay.
לתנא קמא קתני, li-Tanna Kamma katani, so וניבצר מיניה ארבעים ושמונה ve-nivtzar
mineih arba'im u-shmoneh and subtract 48. ומשכחת ליה לחומרא u-meshkachat leih le-chumra
and you'll find your result. וסימנך ve-simanach and the way to know
it is ספרא בצירא safra betzira the sopher again reduces, maybe he
takes away, you know, like he writes words not with their full
letters. תנא תוספא tanna tosfa and the tanna adds. So at once
we're using 48, again what we're doing is we're saying to get
from here to here you add. So to get from מנין שטרות
Minyan Shtarot to חורבן הבית... Churban ha-Bayit... to the חורבן הבית Churban
ha-Bayit number, you add 20 to get to the last two digits.
Okay, from the idea זה לי עשרים שנה בביתך. zeh li esrim
shanah be-veitecha. To get from מנין שטרות Minyan Shtarot to the בריאת
עולם Briyat Olam counting, when we're mostly counting from 4,000, but essentially
בריאת עולם. Briyat Olam. To get from מנין שטרות Minyan Shtarot to
בריאת עולם, Briyat Olam, you add 48. So to get from here
to here you add, to get from here to here you subtract.
The things you add are either 20 or 48. All right, this
is all going to be on the final, so make sure you
get all this. Okay. Anyway,
but now you really know something now. If somebody says מנין שטרות,
Minyan Shtarot, you don't say, "Huh? What? What?" מנין שטרות Minyan Shtarot
actually was continued to be used in בבל Bavel to, like, in
general Jewish society till around the 9th century. It was used in
Egyptian society till, I think, the later, like the 14th century, and
in תימן Teiman till the 20th century, they dated their documents מנין
שטרות. Minyan Shtarot. Yeah, so it is not like, it's interesting historically,
but it actually was a very standard way of counting. Yeah?
Just this lesson of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and we have all
this like how we're not with...
right, well, that was the point they made at the beginning, that
it's a little ironic or, you know, important to acknowledge that even
to the degree we're trying to create the boundaries between us and
larger society, this is just so shaping. We can't totally, we can't
escape it. It shapes the reality in which we live, you know?
So, erase that, I'll take a picture actually.
Okay. You'll get out all the messiness, you'll figure it out? Okay,
fine. All
right, anyway. Okay, so let's take a look. All right, so that's
the מנין שטרות. Minyan Shtarot. Oh, yeah, there was an interesting thing
I saw by looking it up in Hebrew Wikipedia about this, that
the Arabs used this as well. And the Arabs also believed that
it was not about the Seleucid government, they believed, I guess they
got it from the Jews, that it was about when Alexander took
dominion, and they used to call it the counting of the horns.
Why? Because this was such an interesting thing, you know, we know
about the idea
that משה, Moshe, you know, had horns, you know, because משה, Moshe,
whatever, shined, קרן, keren, קרון, keron, etc. you know, Michelangelo's Moses. Anyway,
so apparently they had a similar thing, because Alexander מוקדון, Mokdon, which
is of Macedonia, they mistranslated or whatever as מקרן Makrin or, you
know, from קרן, keren, and then they actually believed that Alexander had
horns. So they called this the counting from the horns, מנין קרנים.
Minyan Karnayim. So anyway, fascinating stuff, things you find out in Hebrew
Wikipedia. All right, anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע האי מאן דלא ידע כמה שני בשבוע
הוא קאי. Amar Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua hai man de-la yada
kamma shani be-shavu'a hu kai. Now it's much easier. You don't know
what year in the שמיטה Shmita cycle you're in. Okay. So here's
the secret. The חורבן הבית Churban ha-Bayit was year one of a
שמיטה Shmita cycle. That's just what, we're just going to take that
for grant for, you know, for fact. What? Makes sense. Okay. So
therefore,
here's an easy way to figure it out.
So טפי חד שתא, tefi chad shata, add one, ונחשוב כללי ביובלי,
ve-nichshov klalei be-yovlei, subtract the hundreds, that's what כללי klalei means, in
the יובל. yovel. Every two יובל yovel is a hundred years. Now
here's the important question. When you have a יובל, yovel, year 50,
is year 50 also year one of the next cycle, or does
year 50 stand by itself? It's actually a debate in the גמרא.
Gemara. The חכמים Chachamim say year 50 stands by itself, year one
starts after. And the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says year 50 is
year one of the next cycle. So it actually would be easier
if we פסקן pasken like the חכמים, Chachamim, you just drop all
the hundreds, right? But we actually, this גמרא's Gemara going to assume
we פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So you actually, so
you take out all of the hundreds, but you have to reserve
two for every century you dropped. Okay? And that's going to get
you. So here's what you do. Figure out how many years it
is from the חורבן הבית. Churban ha-Bayit. Okay, let's say it's 512
years from the חורבן הבית. Churban ha-Bayit. Okay, so add one, so
now you got 513. Now, take out all the hundreds.
ונשדי מינייהו תרי. ve-nishdei mineihu terei. So ונחשוב כללי ביובלי, ve-nichshov klalei
be-yovlei, sort of like, you know, figure all the כללים, klalim, all
the hundreds sort of are correspond to number to יובלים, yovelim, you
remove them all. But
ופרטי בשבועי. u-peratei be-shavu'ei. But the remainder, so here we have let's
say for example it was five hundred years, 518 years since the
חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. So we add one, okay, 519. Now, we
take the hundreds and we attribute the hundreds to the יובל, Yovel,
okay, cause 500 is whatever, 500 years is ten יובלים. Yovels. We
take the פרטים, pratim, the 19, okay,
ונישדי כללי ביובלי ופרטי בשבועי. venishdei klalei beyovlei upratei beshavuei. These 19
we're going to figure out about how many שמיטה Shmita cycles there
were in 19 years, but before we do that, ונשקול מיניה תרי
venishkol minei trei for every hundred that we removed here you have
to take two, cause every bite... so this 500 years is we're
going to have to add 10, by two times five is 10...
29. Okay, so now we've got 29.
Now, ונשקול מיניה תרי, venishkol minei trei, ונשדי אפרטי, venishdei apratei, add
it to the
under-hundred number, ונחשבינהו לפרטי בשבועי, venachshavinehu lepratei beshavuei, and then figure out
how many cycles there are in how many שמיטה Shmita cycles are
in 29, four, plus one, right, remainder one. Okay, so that means
you will be in year one of the שמיטה Shmita cycle. Okay,
וידע כמה שני בשבוע, veyada kama shani beshavua, and you'll know how
many years. So you divide this by seven essentially, 29 divided by
seven is four, remainder one, and therefore you're in year one of
the שמיטה Shmita cycle. Okay, now the reason that works is it
looks confusing, but basically the point is like this. If it is
518 years since the חורבן, Churban, right, and the חורבן Churban was
year one, so think about this. If it was year one in
the חורבן, Churban, it's always easy to go to the easiest case.
If it was year one after the חורבן, Churban, what year would
that be of a שמיטה Shmita cycle? Year two, cause the חורבן
Churban was year one of the שמיטה Shmita cycle. So therefore, you
always take the year from the חורבן, Churban, if it's year one
after the חורבן, Churban, and you add one and that would give
you the number in the שמיטה Shmita cycle. So that's why we
added one. Then we just took out all of the 500, let's
take out, you know, all the שמיטה Shmita cycles, the fifties, but
keeping two years for each. So that's the way it works. So
we added one because the year of the חורבן Churban was year
one, so any year after the חורבן Churban is that plus one,
okay, and then we just threw out the hundreds, kept two for
each hundred, and now we know where we have...
could we just divide 519 by 7?
Could we have divided 519 by? Yes, we could have. Excellent point,
but that would have been more math. Right, but you're absolutely correct.
Right, we could have, because since we're just since yeah, since יובל
Yovel doesn't affect it, we're assuming that with every יובל Yovel it
also begins year one, you're just dividing by seven. So what is
519 divided by seven? So this would be 7, 49, 29, yeah,
74 remainder one.
Absolutely.
I think this is like divide 518 by 7.
Oh,
okay, yeah. 518 plus 1, fine.
Okay, yeah, but let's just...
I don't know, I don't know when we started doing divisions like
this, you know, like the 519.
Well, that's easier if you don't do long division, right? If
you don't have Arabic numbers and it's hard to do long division,
it's much easier to say take out the hundreds and keep I
know, right?
So it's like we are doing...
right, cause this is thanks to the Arabs and thanks to yeah,
thanks to Arabic numerals and long division.
And another thing is that that's why the tradition is at least
is that we know the שמיטה Shmita to this very day, whatever
it is.
Right, the problem is that רמב"ם Rambam has a weird position about
whether you count year fifty as the beginning year or not. רמב"ם
Rambam says depends before חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis and after חורבן הבית.
Churban HaBayis. It's a very strange position in the רמב"ם. Rambam. Anyway,
let's keep on reading. Okay, let's just get to the end here.
וסימנך
כי זה שנתים הרעב בקרב הארץ. vesimanchah ki zeh shenatayim haraav bekerev
haaretz. So the way you remember that basically that you have to
add two years for every hundred you take away is this idea
of these are two years
of famine in the land. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, אחר
ארבע מאות לחורבן הבית, achar arba meos leChurban HaBayis, 400 years after
חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. So remember what the גמרא Gemara says, that
after year 4,000, this is supposed to be the משיח Moshiach period,
when משיח Moshiach could come. So 400 years and this was year
172 after the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. So 400 years after this
is about 230 years into this messianic period. So when you're at
year 400 after the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, 230 years into the
year 4,000, okay, and משיח Moshiach could come any time in the
year 4,000. So, אחר ארבע מאות לחורבן הבית, achar arba meos leChurban
HaBayis, אם יאמר לך אדם, im yomar lecha adam, if somebody tells
you, קח שדה שווה אלף דינרים בדינר, kach sadeh shaveh elef dinarin
bedinar, I have a thousand dollar field I will sell you for
just one dollar, לא תיקח, lo tikach, don't take it, it's a
bad deal, cause משיח Moshiach is going to come by the year
400 after the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, משיח Moshiach will definitely come
and you'll have wasted your money cause you'll be going and living
in Israel. Why you don't want, I don't know, holdings outside of
Israel, I don't know. Anyway, don't do it. לא תיקח. lo tikach.
ומתניתין... umatanitin... ומתניתא תנא, Umatnisa tana, in a ברייתא Baraita we taught,
אחר ארבעת אלפים ומאתים ושלשים ואחת שנה לעולם, Achar arba'as alafim u'masayim
u'shloshim v'achas shanah l'olam, after 4231 years, אם יאמר לך אדם, Im
yomar lecha adam, קח לך שדה Kach lecha sade אלא שוה אלף
דינר בדינר אחד, Ela shaveh elef dinar b'dinar echad, אל תקח, Al
tikach, don't take it. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinayhu? What's the difference between
what was that number? 4231. So 400 years after חורבן הבית, Churban
Habayis, if the year 4000 is חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, 400 years
after חורבן הבית Churban Habayis is 172, well, whatever. If this is
400 years after חורבן הבית Churban Habayis and this was 172 years
after חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, so what will this be? This will
be 4228,
right? 200, yeah. Everybody with me here?
If חורבן, Churban, if the year 4000
is 172 years after חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, then 400 years after
the חורבן הבית Churban Habayis is 4228. Yes? So he said 400
years after חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. This said how many years after
חורבן הבית? Churban Habayis?
4231 after חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
מאי בינייהו? Mai beinayhu? He says 400 after חורבן, Churban, he says
4231 from the creation of the world. So it's a difference of
three years.
מאי בינייהו? Mai beinayhu? איכא בינייהו תלת שנין, Ika beinayhu tlas shanin,
three years. You see? Okay, that's it. All right. Both of these
basically hold משיח Mashiach should have come at around the year, you
know, 400 after the חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, around the year 470,
I guess close, close to the end of the Talmudic period or
something. One said it should have come by 400 after חורבן הבית,
Churban Habayis, one said 4231 after the world was created. They only
are off by three years. Okay.
In this transition between the Romans, Byzantines, and then the Muslims. Right.
Yeah. ומתניתא טפיא תלת שנין U'masnisa tefei tlas shani because this, the
ברייתא Baraita way of talking about it, which is the בריאת עולם,
Beriyas Olam, by saying 4231, that was three years more than the
400 way of counting it. Fine. We are now done basically with
the calendar. Tomorrow we'll just end that last point that the, that
these six years here are going to be understood to be because
it understands this to be when the Greek period begins, and it's
going to understand but that's six years off from the other counting.
It's going to say that this six years the Greek had not
been come yet a world power. So that's really the only thing
we're going to add to this tomorrow. All right, was that fun?
I don't know
about.